This program is brought to you by
Stanford University.
Let's do a little bit of mathematics,
some simple mathematics. Probably most
of you know the mathematics.
The mathematics of spheres.
Spheres in any number of dimensions
are
the special geometries
which are uniform.
And uniform means that they have
constant curvature.
If you have
gone through the previous uh
quarter
you have an idea of what curvature
means.
If you
haven't been through,
you can more or less imagine what
curvature means, and you can imagine
that a sphere
is a very uniform surface.
The curvature at every point is the
same.
But uh let's uh let's just discuss
spheres a little bit.
Which are positively curved surfaces.
And the cosmology
which
is the cosmology of a spherical
universe.
Incidentally, sphere when one talks
about a spherical universe, one is
talking about the geometry of space, not
space-time.
And then we can talk about the
Is it the opposite? Well, the other
possibility, which is the possibility of
negative curvature.
There is also a space which is uniformly
negatively curved. Hard at the
visualize. Harder to draw on the
blackboard, but I'll try to give you
some feel for it. And then the cosmology
which is based on a negatively curved
universe.
And finally, what I would like to do
tonight, well, we may get to more than
that, but uh but at least I would like
to get
to the connection between the equations
that we've written down so far for
cosmology and the general theory of
relativity, Einstein's equations.
So, let's just start, in order to all be
on the same page, with what a sphere is.
And a D-dimensional sphere, D I use for
the for dimension.
Okay, a um
I'll give I'll do it by example.
A two-sphere. One speaks of a
one-sphere, a two-sphere. Let's start
with a one-sphere. A one-sphere, a
two-sphere, a three-sphere, a
four-sphere.
A one-sphere is a one-dimensional
geometry. One-dimensional geometries
just mean curves. Lines. Or curved uh
curves that one-dimensional.
And a one-sphere really just means a
circle.
Okay?
A circle
is a closed curve that comes back on
itself.
But an easy way to describe it is to
just embed it in two dimensions. To
start with a two-dimensional space, X
and Y.
And just write the equation for a
circle, X squared plus Y squared.
X squared plus Y squared
equals R squared in general.
Uh if we're interested in a circle or or
let's call the radius of the circle A.
If the radius of the circle is A, then
on the right-hand side we would just
write A squared.
Uh if we choose if we choose X squared
plus Y squared
equals one, we would call this a unit
circle.
That's the unit circle.
Or the unit one-sphere.
This is the one-sphere of radius A.
And uh that's about all we have to say
about the one-sphere.
The two-sphere
you embed in three dimensions. So, you
start with three dimensions.
X, Y, and Z. These are not to be thought
of
as the three dimensions of ordinary
space.
Ordinary space now is the surface of the
sphere.
For we we should learn now to be
thinking
that space
really means the sphere itself. So, a
world
which is a world on a one-sphere would
be a one-dimensional world with little
bugs moving around on the circle.
The two dimensions is just a crutch. The
two dimensions that you embed it in is
just a crutch for writing an equation
whose solution
is a one-sphere.
But the one-sphere itself is a geometry
or a uh topology really. A geometry on
which you can imagine little creatures
moving around on that one-sphere and
they live in a one-dimensional world.
They would have no idea of
off the sphere either outward or inward.
So,
those would be a that would be a world
of a one-sphere. The world of a
two-sphere begins again with a crutch.
The crutch
could be the crutch of three dimensions,
which we could all which we could call
X, Y, and Z. They would not correspond
to the X, Y, and Z of this room. It's
just a crutch. And you can guess what we
would write. We would write X squared
plus Y squared
plus Z squared equals A squared. That
would be a two-sphere. We should call
this the one-sphere.
Unit one-sphere.
This would be the two-sphere.
Notice that it takes three coordinates
uh or that you you start with the crutch
of three coordinates.
And you
set the sums of the squares of them
equal to the radius squared.
If you
write X squared plus Y squared plus Z
squared equal one,
that becomes the unit two-sphere. This
is the unit
two-sphere.
The hypothesis or the hypothesis that
we're going to investigate a little bit,
or talk about a little bit, is the
possibility now that of course becomes
not a circle,
but a
like the surface of the Earth is a
two-sphere. The hyp-
It's It's not a reasonable hypothesis to
say that we live on the surface of a
two-sphere. Well, actually we do live on
the surface of a two-sphere. It's called
the Earth. But um
from a cosmological point of view, it's
not reasonable to say that we
to think that we might live on a
two-sphere. But it is possible that we
live in a three-sphere.
To construct a three-sphere,
or before I say that, let me let me come
back to the two-sphere for a moment.
Again, the same kind of logic is true.
We're only interested in the surface of
the two-sphere. We imagine that there's
nothing but the surface.
That the rest, the filling of the sphere
and the outside of the sphere, is just
part of the crutch that we used to
construct the the mathematical geometry.
But the mathematical geometry is really
the surface of the sphere.
Okay, a three-sphere constructed exactly
the same way. I don't think I'll write
it. You just invent another letter.
The letter could be W. I don't want to
use T because T gets the this that's too
loaded. It means time. Uh but we would
just make another letter, X, Y, Z, W.
Set the sums of the squares of them
equal to A squared. That would define a
three-sphere. A three-sphere is
difficult to visualize. It's easy to
picture a two-sphere because you can
think of the two-sphere
as embedded in three dimensions.
But the the three-sphere you would have
to think of as embedded in four
dimensions. A little bit harder. But the
mathematics is not much harder. You just
add another letter to the alphabet and
you set the sums of the squares equal to
A squared and you call that a
three-sphere is X squared plus Y squared
plus Z squared plus W squared equals
one.
Now, let me name these geometries.
I'm going to call them omega.
This would be omega one, the one-sphere.
That's a standard common uh terminology.
A sphere is often just referred to as
omega. And this would be omega one, the
one-sphere.
The two-sphere, the three-sphere,
and so forth. But we won't have much
need to be thinking above three
dimensions. Three dimensions is a space
in any case.
All right, that's one way of thinking of
spheres. Another way is to concentrate
directly on the surface itself. The uh
and not to think of it as embedded. And
to describe it in terms of a metric.
To describe the surface in terms of
coordinates
which are purely in the sphere.
For example, the surface of the Earth
would not be described by X, Y, and Z,
but by longitude and latitude, two
angles.
And to represent the sphere by a metric.
So, let's uh let's um in fact begin with
the simplest case, which is the
one-sphere.
Uh
if I take a unit one-sphere, I could
describe it
just by an angle phi. I could describe
the points along that sphere
along that one sphere by angles phi.
Now, phi goes from 0 to 2 pi in this
case.
0 to 2 pi.
If it's a unit one sphere, we would just
write that distance
We could write a metric. The metric
would be very simple. If it's a unit one
sphere,
then metric is just equal to d phi
squared.
The distance along the unit one sphere
is just proportional to the angle.
We are
uh and just to keep everything positive,
I've squared it. It would just be d phi
squared.
Okay? That would be the metric of a one
sphere.
Now, let's go to a two sphere. Now, the
way to think about a two sphere
is to imagine
a series of one spheres. Here's the
picture. I'll draw it first with my
hands. Imagine a two sphere. Okay?
And think of it by starting at the North
Pole. Okay, I'll start at the North Pole
and start with a little circle and then
expand the circle and then contract the
circle. So, it's a sequence of one
spheres
where the sequence begins at one pole
and ends at the other pole. And of
course, it doesn't matter. You don't
have to take the North Pole and the
South Pole. You can take the East Pole
and the West Pole, but uh
uh
or any other
I guess the East Pole and the West Pole
is not a
the right thing, but any any two points.
But, think of the two sphere. Sorry,
think of the two sphere as a series of
one spheres or one sphere parameter a
series of one spheres parameterized by
another angle. Now,
the new angle, the angle
around the one sphere still goes from 0
to 2 pi.
But, the angle the new angle that goes
from the North Pole to the South Pole,
that only goes from 0 to pi. In other
words, from 0 to 180°.
North Pole would be 0, South Pole would
be 180° or vice versa.
All right. And so, here's the way to
write the metric. First of all, let's
draw a picture.
Here's
the two sphere and think of it as a kind
of series of one spheres. I've started
at the East Pole instead of the North
Pole.
Uh
All right. And so, we introduce another
angle. First of all, there's phi, which
goes around.
But, now there's theta. Let's call it
theta,
which goes from one end of the sphere to
the other end of the sphere. Let's call
this end theta equals 0.
And let's call this end theta equals pi.
All right. So, let's first write the All
right, let's try to write the metric
now. It's not too hard to write a write
the metric.
First of all, if we move in the theta
direction along the theta direction,
then d s squared is just d theta
squared.
If you move
along the north-south
um
direction along
uh the theta axis,
sorry, along the theta direction from
north to south, the distance that you
move is proportional to the angle that
you move by.
But, then
the other term in the metric has to do
with moving in the perpendicular
direction, the perpendicular direction
being around the phi axis. This is
theta.
Around the phi axis, which is like the
one sphere,
which is like going around the one
sphere,
the radius of each one of these one
spheres, each one of these circles is
different.
All right. It's different. So, each one
of these is not a unit one sphere,
but the radius of the sphere the sorry,
the radius of the circle varies from
this end where it's 0
back to this end where it's 0.
But, in between, what's it given by?
Sine of theta.
Sine of theta varies smoothly from 0
back to 0
going through a maximum at 90° and then
coming back to 0. So, the radius of the
one spheres
or the circles,
the radius coming in
replacing this
radius here
is sine
squared of theta
d phi squared.
All right. So, that's the familiar and
many of you are familiar with this
metric. This is the metric of a
two-dimensional ordinary two-dimensional
sphere. Take any two points close to
each other separated by a given interval
in theta and an interval an
infinitesimal interval in theta and an
infinitesimal interval in phi and you
want to find the distance between them.
Then, the square of the distance is d
theta squared plus sine squared theta d
phi squared.
Now,
from there, you go to the three sphere.
The three sphere is just a series of two
spheres.
So, we imagine we have a two sphere.
Imagine we Now now I cannot I I can't
draw it easily and I can't even use my
hands properly to do it. But, imagine a
series of two spheres where you start
with a two sphere,
you blow it up and then you shrink it
back to 0. That's a three-dimensional
geometry. It takes three angles to
describe it.
Two to describe any one of the two of
the two spheres, but then another angle.
And that other angle or that other
variable also starts at 0,
blows up, not blows up, but increases
until it comes to a maximum and then
shrinks back down to 0.
That's the idea of the three sphere.
And to make a three sphere, you just
introduce one more angle.
Let's call it alpha.
This is the three sphere. This is the
two sphere, one sphere.
And it's the unit one sphere, in fact.
This is the unit two sphere.
What Why don't I give it its right It's
uh
Let's just call it
d omega one squared. That's the notation
that one usually writes for the metric
of a unit one sphere.
And the same notation, this would become
the metric
d omega two squared.
That's the definition of this side.
Uh omega two is really a whole sphere
and this is simply a symbol that stands
for what's here.
But, it represents the metric of a unit
two sphere.
All right. What about a three sphere?
Introduce another angle. And now I'm
going to call the other angle alpha.
Do exactly the same thing. Alpha varies
from 0 to 2 pi, but at every point of
alpha, we have a two sphere.
All right. What's the What's the metric?
The metric is d alpha squared.
Now, the radius of that two sphere
varies again, increases and then
decreases.
And you have to write
sine squared of alpha this time.
Not d phi squared, but d omega two
squared.
Let me write this d phi squared. Instead
of writing it d phi squared, let's call
it d omega one squared.
So, notice
each time you increase the
dimensionality
of the sphere, you add another angle
and then
you think of it as a series of lower
dimensional spheres with a radius which
varies from 0 to a maximum back to 0.
That's the sine of alpha. You square it
to get the metric.
And then, you write the metric of a unit
one dimensional less sphere.
This would be
d s squared
for the three sphere.
Let me write it out explicitly just to
make sure that
you understand exactly explicitly what
this means.
It means
d alpha squared for the
d s squared for the three sphere
is equal to d alpha squared,
that's the extra angle we add,
plus sine squared of alpha and then open
up a box and just write
the previous
metric
of the lower dimensional sphere.
And just call this thing here d omega
two squared.
All right. You can go on with this. I'll
tell you what the general answer is.
The general answer is
if you want the the D sphere,
for example, the four sphere, we just
write the same thing, the alpha squared
plus sine squared alpha times the metric
of the three sphere, of the unit three
sphere.
And so, by induction, we can go to the
metric of any dimensional sphere, but
we'll never need more than the three
dimensional sphere
unless during the course of this lecture
series
an announcement is made in the New York
Times that it is discovered that the
world is four or five or six
dimensional. Well, they do that all the
time, but uh
uh
but not in the sense in which
uh in which I mean.
Okay, that is the idea of a higher
dimensional sphere.
Once you think of it this way, you you
can forget the crutch of how it's
embedded
in a in the higher dimensional space.
Notice that the one sphere is described
by one variable, one coordinate, phi.
You don't need X and Y. The two sphere
is described by two coordinates, theta
and phi. Well,
okay, this is d phi squared.
The three sphere by three coordinates.
And we've lost all memory
uh of whether or not the sphere is
embedded in a higher dimensional space,
and we will so we will we will consider
it not to be. It's just an abstract
description of a geometry.
Uh
Now, this geometry has special features,
as I said.
It's uniformly curved. It's everywhere
the same as it every other point.
For example, there are other kinds of
geometries that we could draw
not draw, but describe, which would have
different metrics, perhaps some simple
deformations of this metric. Put some
wrong coefficient, some other
coefficient, or put some other function
besides sine squared theta,
which still goes from zero back to zero.
You'll be making some sort of deformed
sphere. For example, you could make an
ellipsoid. An ellipsoid is a nice a very
nice surface, all right, but it's not
uniform. It's different at some places
than in other places. It has places
where the curvature is larger and places
where the curvature is smaller.
The sphere is rather special in that
it's uniform. Wherever you are on the
sphere is the same as it every other
point. So, it's called homogeneous,
just like a cosmology.
Okay, now, these are
unit spheres. Each one of these
is a unit
three sphere, two sphere, one sphere.
Supposing we now want to make a sphere
of radius A, the metric of a radius
sphere of radius A,
then all we have to do is
take the
the metric of the unit sphere and
multiply it by the square of the radius
of the sphere. Why the square? The
square because the metric here is
associated with the square of the
radius,
uh or the square of the distance.
And so, if we actually wanted a
let's say a three sphere
of radius A, we would take this whole
thing
and multiply it by A.
All right, so we would write
squared.
Thank you.
A squared.
Okay. So, I can we can write it this
way. We can write that d s squared
for a sphere of radius A is just equal
to A squared
times d omega
And let's take let's now fix ourselves
to the three sphere.
But it doesn't matter, whatever
whatever dimension we're talking about.
Three, four, five, one, two.
Incidentally, what is a zero sphere?
Two points. Why is it two points? Let
let let's just for fun, let's ask what a
zero sphere is.
It seems like a stupid idea,
a zero sphere.
I mean,
a one sphere almost seems sort of silly.
It's just a circle.
Um
A zero a zero sphere is zero
dimensional.
All right? But the way to figure out
what it is is just to extrapolate this
formula back one step.
So, if a one sphere is x squared plus y
squared equals a squared, and a two
sphere is a x squared plus y squared
plus z squared equals a squared, then a
zero sphere must just be x squared
equals a squared. Or, let's take the
unit zero sphere.
The unit zero sphere is x squared equals
one.
What are the solutions of x squared
equals one?
Plus or minus one.
All right? So, a zero sphere is just two
points.
And notice, it's kind of interesting
that the one sphere can be made from the
zero sphere by taking a sequence of
zero spheres. Here's the first zero
sphere, here's the next zero sphere,
here's the next zero sphere. Here's the
one of maximal radius, and then we come
back to the zero sphere, which is small.
So,
the Now, don't ask me what a a minus one
sphere is. That one I can't do.
But I'm sure that mathematicians have a
uh
have a definite Well, I'm not sure.
Actually, I've never heard of a minus
one sphere.
I've heard of a horn sphere.
Have you heard of a horn sphere?
Yes, the boundary of the zero sphere.
What is a horn sphere? Nah.
The minus one sphere. Oh, a minus one
sphere.
Yeah, it's the
Yeah.
Uh
Negative dimensions is never
interesting. I don't I I don't think it
is.
Fractional dimensions is sometimes
interesting.
Okay.
Now, let's think about cosmology.
And let's think about the cosmology of a
world
where space
is a three sphere.
We're not interested in space now, we're
interested in space time.
And what this space time is describing
is a space of variable radius, a space
whose radius changes with time.
Uh the Big Bang theory, for example,
could be considered a theory in which
the world is a three sphere, which
starts out extremely small. How small?
Well, let's uh let's say um
the Planck size or some some arbitrarily
small size, even zero,
and expands and expands and expands and
expands. It may or may not come back and
implode on itself. We're going to talk
about that.
But don't get the idea that we're
thinking in any sense about a
a higher dimensional sphere when we
embed it in time. Time is different.
Don't try to conflate time with one of
these dimensions here. Then you get in
trouble.
Okay, so let's talk about the cosmology
and the metric of a geometry of an
expanding or contracting or time
variable sphere.
Well, all we have to do well, we first
write down
proper time now.
This is the space time interval. The
space time interval is the proper time,
just as in special relativity.
And as always,
it starts out with a positive term, d t
squared, which we can take to be just d
t squared.
You can change variables. For example,
you can take some other function of the
time
uh so that there would be some
coefficient in front here, but you don't
there's no no particular reason to do
that. It starts out with d t squared,
and then
that's the metric associated with the
clock.
This is the thing which reads off clock
time, and then minus
the space metric,
which is A of T
squared, the time dependent radius of
the spherical universe,
times d omega three squared. Now, let me
say one more thing about these
coordinates.
As I said, there's nothing special about
any particular point on the sphere. Uh
let's draw a two sphere.
For the two sphere, we would write the
two sphere exactly the same way,
except and put instead of putting
d omega two here, we would put d omega
one squared here.
That's the only difference. Um
Okay.
It's convenient
Well, not it's convenient to focus, as I
said, on one of the poles of the sphere
and think of it as the place where we
are. Us. Where we are. One of the poles
of the sphere. In other words, the
coordinate ties the sphere
in such a way that we are at the North
Pole.
Now, there's nothing special about that
North Pole and presumably there's
nothing special about our own location.
It's just a definition of where we are.
We are at the North Pole of the sphere.
That means we are
I guess the North Pole is over on this
side.
I'm sorry for the fact that North isn't
vertical, but that's also an arbitrary
tradition that uh
somebody invented in the past.
Um That's where they do it in Russia.
Well, the reason I did it this way is
because
yeah, it's usually the case that we put
the North Pole at the top, but we also
usually measure angles from the
horizontal.
So,
so I had to compromise somehow. So, I
put the North Pole
over on the right.
North Pole, South Pole over here. Okay.
What was my point? My point is here is
So,
as as a convention, no no no real um
um
uh um
invariant significance to this, but we
are over here. Us, the you the US, us.
Okay, we're over here. And that means
that alpha
which measures distance, which measures
angle away from us
can be sort of thought as of as a radial
distance away from us.
On the on the unit sphere, it's not the
radial distance measured in kilometers
or any other units, but it's the it's
the measure
a dimensionless measure on the unit
sphere.
And it can sort of be thought of as
radial distance.
Here's lines
of fixed radial distance from us.
So, alpha can be thought of and it's
useful to think of it
as distance from us or or a coordinate
which represents um
which represents the radial coordinate
away from us in space.
Okay, so here we are.
Here's the metric.
We can plug in the omega 3
times a of t squared. The only
difference now between this
and this is that a is time dependent and
represents the time dependence of the
radius of the universe, if you like, the
spatial radius of the universe.
This geometry, and it's very simple.
That's all That's all there is to it. I
mean of course it is
more complicated than that in a certain
sense.
Just as
the Earth is full of little
irregularities and so forth that would
make the metric of the surface of the
Earth quite irregular, so too is the
universe irregular because of the
presence of galaxies and stars and other
lumpies things.
But apart from those small lumps,
this is all there is to the metric of a
universe which is spherical, spatially
spherical.
This is called
well, the geometry both the geometry and
the cosmology based on it is called
Friedman-Robertson-Walker.
And some people put an L in there for
Lemaître.
Um I got used to calling it FRW and I
will not
speak the names of the of any of those
people
because if I leave if I if I speak the
names, I will leave out one important
one, Lemaître. It's just everybody just
says FRW.
So, it's an FRW universe
with spherical spatial shape.
Okay. It has positive curvature, not
positive space-time curvature. Positive
spatial curvature.
Right? To indicate that it has positive
spatial curvature,
we sometimes write that it has k equal
to plus one. Now, what is it that's plus
one? Nothing is plus one. It's just This
means curvature positive.
Okay, that's all there is to
the geometry
of the sphere.
But I want to describe spheres a little
more. I want to give you a little a
little further picture
of of thinking about spheres and
especially looking at spheres and
looking out
at the world around you
from the North Pole, so to speak.
Um maybe I'm talking maybe I'm looking
out at the world from the South Pole.
Yeah, I have a feeling in my drawings
I'm going to put us at the South Pole.
Now, I'm really going to put the South
Pole at the bottom.
Why is the South Pole at the bottom and
the North Pole at the top?
Because people from the Northern
Hemisphere are drawing the maps.
No. It's because if you take a map and
you turn it upside down
and you draw it upside down, just do it.
And you'll notice you'll notice that
South America is sort of unstable. It
South America hangs from North America.
North America doesn't hang from South
America.
A very bright friend of mine used to
think that all rivers ran north and
south. He was thinking of the Nile.
Look.
Uh I owe a friend who's about a famous
physicist
who had two beliefs in his life.
One of the beliefs is don't matter what
direction he was driving, it was always
north.
The other the other thing that he
believed when he was young
was that cats were female dogs.
I'm going to tell you his name. His name
is Willy Fischler. He was a good friend
of mine.
He's not probably not after he sees
this.
Uh yeah, FRW This is an FRW k equals
plus one universe.
Means positively curved and of this
special kind.
Uh let's talk a little bit more about
spheres.
There
when you make a map of the Earth, you
would like to lay the map out
on um
on a flat plane.
And you'd like to do it in a nice way
that preserves shapes and so forth.
There are various ways to do that.
There's Mercator projections uh
and other kinds of projections that
project the the sphere onto the plane,
they always distort sizes.
You can't You can't stretch the sphere
out onto a plane without uh distorting
it. But there's there's one particular
mathematical construction which is
probably the nicest mathematical
construction. It's not good for
cartographers.
And the reason is it requires an
infinite plane to draw the
uh surface of the Earth
in a stereographic projection. So, let
me show you a ster- what a stereographic
projection looks like.
And it it is somewhat useful to draw
this because
when I get to the negative curved side,
about all I'll be able to tell you about
it to draw it will be to draw the analog
of the um of the stereographic
projection.
All right, the stereographic projection
is done in the following way. Here's the
mathematical construction. You can do
this with a a sphere of any dimension,
incidentally, but uh let's take a uh a
two-sphere. So, here's a two-sphere.
If it's a two-sphere, I'm not going to
bother drawing lines of longitude and
latitude.
It uh it is a two-sphere. It's not a
one-sphere.
And think of it as resting on
an infinite plane
with the
I guess we'll call it the South Pole.
With the South Pole tangent and just
touching the plane.
All right, now.
I want to construct a mapping from the
sphere onto the plane.
From the sphere to the plane so that
every point on the sphere is represented
uniquely by a single point on the plane.
And there's an easy way to do that.
It's going to have a bit of problems
about the North Pole. But apart from the
North Pole, every point will be will be
will be located on the plane in a unique
way.
And the way to do it is to Let me see if
I have some colored chalk, yeah?
Go pick a point, any point at all on the
sphere.
Go to the North Pole
and draw a straight line. Now, this is
not a straight line
which means it's not a geodesic in the
sphere.
It is in really in three dimensions.
Draw a straight line
from the North Pole to the point and
continue it till it hits the plane.
Identify
this point on the sphere
with the corresponding point on the
plane.
Every point on the sphere
will be
represented
by a unique point on the plane.
The South Pole of the sphere
will be right at the origin of the of
the plane. It's just the North Pole of
the sphere,
which is going to have a bit of problem.
As you go out to the North Pole, as you
get closer and closer to the North Pole,
the image on the plane moves out.
Moves out to far further and further and
further away.
Okay? In fact, if you approach the North
Pole from different directions,
the image on the plane
goes way way out to infinite distances
in in a in a way that
This point very close to the North Pole
over here has its image way out over
here.
A point over here has its image way out
over here. So, the North Pole has a
little bit of difficulty.
And mathematicians have a way of dealing
with it. They simply say, "Infinity is a
single point."
They say, "Infinity, we'll just call it
the point at infinity."
What we really mean is the North Pole of
the sphere.
Okay. Now, let's draw some figures.
First of all, let's draw Antarctica.
Antarctica is down here.
And this is in the approximation of a
perfectly circular Antarctica.
Here's Antarctica.
It will look like a little let's yeah,
let's and let's redraw it over here
on the plane. Here's the plane
looking at the plane head on.
Here's Antarctica.
Antarctica simply looks like a little
circle.
Now, of course, there's the Arctic
Circle up here or the or the North Polar
ice cap,
which still exists a little bit.
The North Polar ice cap looks entirely
different. It's way way out far. I I
didn't give myself enough room. It's way
way out far like that.
And as you get closer and closer to the
North Pole, as the North Polar ice cap
shrinks,
this this circle will get bigger and
bigger.
Okay?
But imagine that the North Polar ice cap
is is actually the same size really,
meaning in the real Earth or on the real
sphere is the same size as here. So,
there's clearly a distortion of sizes.
Let's put another continent over here
and
the continent over here,
which by assumption in this model world
here has the same size. All continents
have the same size.
The same size as Antarctica. Well, when
we draw them
on the plane here,
the
Antarctica will look like the smallest
one. As we move away, they'll look
bigger.
As we move the continents which are
close to the North Pole here, they will
look gigantic.
So, the further out we go,
the bigger these things will look
on this plane.
Now, straight lines are geodesics that
emanate from the South Pole here, those
are just great circles.
Those are just great circles and lines
of constant longitude. They look like
straight lines here in this picture.
They just look like this.
And they're characterized by a
a angle of longitude.
Now, what the main thing I want you to
notice now,
and which is more or less obvious, is
that if you were at the center, let's
put us at the South Pole now. This time
we're at the South Pole and we're
looking out around the world,
we see angular sizes
which are distorted relative to the size
of the object. In other words,
this object over here looks too big to
us. When we look at it, it subtends too
large an angle compared with flat space.
Compared with flat space,
this object will look too big to us.
What's actually happening
is
that
well,
what's actually happening is that the
sums of squares of the sums of the
angles of a triangle is bigger than 180°
on a curved surface like this.
And so, if we were to draw triangles
here,
the angles would be bigger than they
would be in flat space. But from the
point of view of an astronomer looking
out, let's suppose that that astronomer
was looking out at a structure out
there, which he happened to know was the
same size as our galaxy. For some
reason, he sees a galaxy out there,
which looks very similar to our galaxy.
Has the same kind of structure. Has good
reason to believe that that galaxy is
very similar to our own.
When he looks at it,
he will see an angle in the sky which is
bigger than he would see if the space
was flat.
All right, that's something to keep in
in mind because that's basically the way
we determine whether space is curved or
not.
By looking at angles of things whose
size we think we know. Now, it's not
galaxies.
Galaxies are not good measuring rods.
First of all, that we we can't not for
not for deep cosmic distances. But there
are other objects
that we can that we can detect whose
size we have reason to believe we know
and whose angle in the sky we can
detect.
Yeah, we have to know the distance, too.
Right. So,
knowing the angle in the sky is not
sufficient to tell you anything. You
need to know the angle and how far away
you are. And another question. How far
away they were when they
Yeah, that
that's that's exactly
Well,
turns out that cancels out. But
another question does
do circles on the surface of the sphere
project as circles? Yeah, they do.
No no circles.
Circles. It's one of the nice things
about the Okay.
Yeah.
Circles project as circles.
That's a feature of stereographic
mappings.
Yeah, all circle it's obvious for
horizontally oriented circles.
Not so obvious for other circles, but
it's true. True anyway.
So, that means
a continent would would have the same or
would it or would it not have the same
shape a non-circle? Okay, there's
there's two state there's two
statements, both of which are true.
Slightly different. First of all, it is
true that circles project as circles.
Okay? That's it.
But
if you're talking about arbitrary
shapes, then this is a weaker statement,
but still a true statement. The weaker
statement is
small things. And now you have to think
about differentially small things, but
small
small objects will have the same shape.
Same shape means same ratio of sides and
so forth. So, this is a shape
preserving, at least for small shapes.
It's a shape preserving mapping.
Angles are preserved. Angles perfect.
Angles are preserved. Yeah.
There's a word for angle preserving,
conformal.
This is a conformal mapping. Not all
conformal mappings preserve circles,
incidentally,
but this one does.
It's conformal.
The Mercator projection is also
conformal.
And so,
continents have the right shape as long
as they're not too big, they have the
right shape,
but they have the wrong relative size.
Same thing here.
Okay, that's that's
about everything we need to know about
spheres.
Now, let's spend a little time with the
I call it the opposite of a sphere. It's
not the opposite of a sphere. Another
geometry which has negative curvature.
And I'm going to tell you how to
construct it. I'm not going to derive
this.
I will tell you what the metric is for a
negatively curved
analog of a sphere.
And then I will draw you the analog not
of we can also do the stereographic
projection, but I'll show you what the
stereographic projection or the analog
of the stereographic projection looks
like.
And I will assign it as a homework task
to be turned in next time when I'm gone,
incidentally.
Get
I I better tell you right now.
Back to England.
Next No, just yeah, I'll do next next
week.
Next week. Next week. Next week I'll be
gone.
Uh but then I'm then I'm finished. I'm
not going anywhere
after that.
Not for a while anyway.
Uh
this was
just a very, very bad timing. I wasn't
watching what I was doing and I
answered some emails too quickly and
said yes.
And I didn't realize they were all
within weeks of each other. Italy, so
Russia, England,
and uh back and forth like a a nutcase.
My doctor said, "You're crazy. You're
going to kill yourself."
If I'm dead, hold the class anyway.
Yes, all right. Negative curved space.
All right.
First thing about negative curved space,
well, all right, let's let's not go
let's let's do the first thing last.
Um
Yeah.
The metric of a negatively curved space,
uniform negative curvature.
It's pretty unique.
It's pretty unique, much like the
sphere.
Uh uniform negative curved space.
And
it's related to the metric of
the sphere in an extremely simple way in
every dimension.
Whatever dimension, let's let's write
the general formula
for the sphere first.
sin alpha squared times
let's times d omega
of one less dimension.
d minus one
squared.
That's
d omega d squared. Is this clear what
this means?
That uh that you take a sphere of one
less dimension, you know, capital d is
usually reserved for space-time
dimension,
but I don't mean the space-time
dimension here. I mean the just the
space dimension.
Hm?
Uh
I don't mind n. You want me to write n?
Sure. n I don't care.
It it it doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter.
Uh
It's a It's a correct formula no matter
what we call the uh the thing here. The
heart. So, this is
This is the way you go from one sphere
to the next.
The
negative curved version is called the
hyperbolic plane.
What it has to do with hyperbolas, don't
worry about. Maybe I'll get a chance to
tell you what it has to do with
hyperbolas.
Um
but uh
the hyperbolic plane
is the analog of the sphere with
negative uh curvature. And I'll tell you
very simply how to get it. You replace
the the sign of alpha. You don't You
don't change this.
You don't change this.
Okay? But you change the sign of alpha
to something else.
What you change the sign of alpha to is
the hyperbolic sign of alpha.
This is not a sphere anymore.
Furthermore, one other thing.
The um the sign function, of course,
really is a function of an angle
typically.
No.
We will call this This is the omega.
I'll tell you why in a moment. But this
is now not called d omega d, but it's
called d script h
d
squared.
The h stands for hyperbolic.
And it's not as universal a notation as
this is,
but it's called the hyperbolic plane.
All right.
Now, one important difference
is in this formula, alpha goes from the
North Pole to the South Pole and varies
between zero and pi.
In this formula, alpha goes from zero to
infinity.
Sines are periodic functions. They come
back to themselves, or at least sine
sine being zero comes back to itself
after alpha becomes equal to pi.
So, you shrink
You start from zero size and you go back
to zero size.
The hyperbolic sine is not a periodic
function.
And alpha just goes from zero to
infinity.
Okay.
All right.
Goes from zero to infinity, number one.
I'm going to write down what the meaning
of hyperbolic sine is for those who
don't know. It's a very simple function.
The sine the hyperbolic sine
of a
variable alpha, which is not an angle
anymore. It's not an angle anymore.
It's just by definition e to the alpha
plus e to the minus alpha
divided by two. What?
Minus.
Thank you.
I would have made that mistake. Minus.
e to the other It's the analog of the
statement that sine of alpha is e to the
i alpha minus e to the minus i alpha
over 2i.
All right, but we don't need to We don't
particularly need this formula here.
So, I'm sorry. In the metric for the
data for space, is that the
lower dimensional
differential d d? Where where are we?
Sorry, which
which which which blackboard do you
want? The differential associated with
sine of hyperbolic cosine.
Here? Yeah, over there. The the
differential that you're promoting to
the Yeah, right there.
This side?
d minus one. d omega
Yeah.
This is correct.
That's That's That's spherical there, is
that right?
Yeah, that's a regular sphere.
All right, I'll tell you what's going on
here. And then we'll get to what's going
on. I'll explain what's going on in a
moment, but let me just tell you the
mathematical facts and then we'll think
about what they mean.
Okay.
Alpha goes from zero to infinity.
When alpha is zero,
the hyperbolic sine is zero, so is the
ordinary sine. These two cancel for
alpha equals zero. So, the hyperbolic
sine
begins very much like the sine,
but then instead of turning over and
coming back to zero,
it exponentially increases.
e to the minus alpha When alpha gets
large, e to the minus alpha gets very
small, so this is negligible, but e to
the plus alpha grows.
And so for large alpha,
this is basically just e to the alpha
over two, and it just grows.
All right.
So, one of the things that's saying
is that the size
of this
Think about the sphere first.
As the angle alpha increases for the
sphere,
the lower dimensional sphere grows and
then shrinks. Grows a little modestly,
stops growing, and then shrinks.
Uh in the mathematical sense.
Here, as you move away from the origin,
as you move away from us, again, we'll
put us at the center.
Us at alpha equals zero.
As we move away, the size of the spheres
around us get bigger and bigger and
bigger very rapidly.
All right.
So, think of ourselves at the center.
If we want to know the distance to a
point radially outward, that's mainly
just d alpha squared. That's d alpha.
That's this part here.
But if we look around us at the sky,
what do we see? We see a two sphere. The
sky is a two sphere.
And it's described by two angles.
But the size of that two sphere
in the in the in the uh spherical case,
the the size of the two spheres we look
deeper and deeper into space gets bigger
and then gets smaller.
Here, the size of the two sphere grows
very rapidly.
So, as we look out far away,
the
uh the size of the sphere that we see is
exponentially growing in this geometry
here.
This is the
definition, or it's not the definition
of the hyperbolic plane, but for our
purposes, this is the definition, but
I'm going to draw you a picture of what
it looks like. Now,
uh if you want a much better picture
than I can draw, there's a very famous
picture of the hyperbolic plane. It's
the one I like best. Um
it's Escher's drawing.
And just look this up on Just just plug
this into your uh Google.
Uh M. C. Escher, and the drawing is
called limit uh, limit circle number
four.
IV
Studying that picture will tell you more
about cosmology than uh, than any of
these equations, or at least the
cosmology of negative curved spaces.
But, I'm going to do my best to draw
something that looks, roughly speaking,
like Escher's drawing. This is sometimes
also called angels and devils, but
angels and devils is a different
drawing.
It's a bunch of
only Escher can do these things.
But, uh, what it is
All right.
You You start with a disc.
Now, this What this is is it's actually
the analog of the um, stereographic
projection.
The stereographic projection here
goes out to infinity.
The North Pole is
Although the North Pole is really not
very far away.
On the stereographic projection, it
looks like it's very far away.
And every continent appears to get
bigger and bigger as you move far
further and further away.
Exactly the opposite is true for the
negatively curved spaces.
What looks like it's not very far away
is infinitely far away.
Okay?
What look
uh, and
the continents, which are or galaxies or
whatever they are, let's call them
continents, all of which, by assumption,
have the same size, look smaller and
smaller as you go away.
So, Escher doesn't draw continents, he
draws angels and devils in some in some
devilishly clever way.
The first devil is about
the one near the center is about that
big.
And then you move out a little bit, and
the next set of double devils or angels
are about that big.
Now,
they really are the same size in the
same sense
that
Antarctica is about as big as what?
Australia, maybe?
I don't know.
But, of course, Australia looks much
bigger on this uh, type of projection.
Okay? Here,
Antarctica has a certain size,
but Australia, which is the same size,
and now there are lots of Australias
around here.
Uh, more Australia more potential places
for Australias.
Here, there's a certain number of
possible places for Australia.
Here, there are more places because the
sphere the two sphere is getting bigger
and bigger
exponentially fast.
The next layer of
continents
looks even smaller.
And the next layer looks even smaller.
I'm going to draw half of this and throw
the other half away cuz I get tired of
drawing it.
And as you get closer and closer to this
boundary, which is not really a
boundary, they look smaller and smaller
and smaller.
Each one of these continents is the same
size
geometrically.
All right.
So, that means if you want to know how
far it is from the center to the
boundary, all you have to do is count
the number of continents that you cross.
But, the number of continents that you
cross is infinite because they get
smaller and smaller and smaller.
So, the distance to the boundary,
although in this picture, it looks like
the distance to the boundary is finite,
whereas in this picture, it looks like
the distance to the boundary or the
North Pole is infinite, it's really
quite the opposite.
Really, the North Pole is not very far
here.
In fact, if you count the continents
because they get bigger and bigger,
you would pass a finite number of
continents before you got out to
infinity.
Here,
it looks like the end of the world is
not very far away,
but if you count continents,
there will be an infinite number, and so
this is really an infinite geometry.
This is really an infinite space
with an infinite volume.
This space has finite volume.
And but one thing which is common for
both of them
is that they are homogeneous.
This doesn't look homogeneous. It looks
like these continents have different
size and this continent over here, but
in fact, we know from the fact that it
really is a sphere, we know that every
point is the same as every other point.
It's not obvious, but it's also true
here. Every continent is like every
other continent. That means
that there are symmetries of this figure
where you can move this continent to
here,
this one will move to here.
There are symmetries, which are the
analog of rotations of the sphere, for
example.
Rotations of the sphere will move the
South Pole to here.
Something else will come and take the
place of the South Pole.
There are symmetries of this figure
which move the South Pole
out to some other place over here, and
meantime, they move some other place to
the South Pole, and the whole figure
shifts, but the geometry, the intrinsic
geometry of it doesn't change. So, this
is again a homogeneous space of uniform
curvature,
but if you were to calculate the
you would find it's negative.
Now, a question you might ask is
incidentally,
this
I've drawn the case of
H2.
Two dimensions. I cannot so easily draw
H3, but it's made the same way.
You take a three-dimensional
ball, and you fill it
with smaller balls, first this one this
size, and you just make a
three-dimensional version of this.
It's It's not too hard to figure out
what that means. You make a
three-dimensional version of ball at the
center this big, balls surrounding it on
all sides, which are smaller,
more balls surrounding it, which are yet
smaller, and so forth. Same pattern.
And that would make H3 for you.
This is H2. Now, I forgot what I was
going to say about it. I was going to
say something else about it, but I don't
remember what it was. So, an observer in
any one of those circles would see a
similar pattern. Would see what? A
similar pattern. Yeah, they see exactly
the same thing. Exactly the same thing.
And it is very, very instructive to take
Escher's drawing and just look at it for
a while, and uh,
and um,
uh, uh,
yeah. As you
As you look at
in the spherical case, things seem to be
bigger than they are. Right.
Here, they're smaller.
Yeah, this here sphere is the same size
as that sphere.
Okay? That means if a if a telescope was
pointed at the two extremities of this
galaxy over here,
I'm going from galaxies to continents to
angels and devils, but all the same
stuff. Uh, if you were to point your
telescope and see what the angle
subtended, you would tend to see a
smaller
angle than you would in flat the size
and the distance of some object out
here,
in the positively curved space, it would
look too big. Now, too means relative to
flat space.
In a negative curved geometry, it would
look too small.
All right. So, that's that's basically
the way that we tell whether space is
uh,
uh, is curved or not by looking at those
angles. Yeah.
Is the relevance of the stereographic
projection that the
that the astronomer can construct those
from the observations? Is that the
Yeah. Is that what it Yeah, I mean,
astronomer can construct it from the
observations.
And it turns out that you say the Do you
have to fold in the fact that it changes
with time? And
whether you have to fold in the fact
that it changes with time. In fact, no,
you really don't, but uh,
but that's a separate issue.
Let's forget for the moment the fact
that it's time dependent. Yeah, the
astronomer does The astronomer is a
surveyor who surveys triangles in the
sky,
and measures angles.
I mean, it's not It's not usual for
surveyors to create stereographic
projections
of things, but that seems to be what
That's because
that's because surveyors
usually survey small portions of the
surface of the Earth.
And so, the overall curvature is not
important.
Um,
if we were in the business of surveying
large
pieces of the Earth,
well, we have our choice. Of course, we
could build ourselves a globe, and
but if we wanted to put it on a flat
page
we would have to do some sort of
projection.
The
the um
what's it called the the
the Mercator projection
is a nice one for maps
but for those
self-centered people who like to think
of themselves at the center of the
universe
this is better.
The uh
In other words, for astronomers who
literally look out around them
and they do want to prejudice their
drawings by putting themselves at the
center
then the stereographic projection is
more convenient than the analog of the
Mercator Mercator projection.
Okay, so there were there's there's
that's the mathematics of negative well
the uh
intuitive mathematics of negative
curvature
keep in mind
that although
the projection of the sphere looks
infinite it's really describing the
finite sphere
whereas the projection of the hyperbolic
plane looks finite it's really
describing a space which is infinite.
All right.
Cosmology based on space
which has negative curvature
is usually called
infinite.
FRW infinite negative curved FRW
So, what does
infinite negative curved FRW
look like as a mathematical metric?
Same deal.
The tau squared is equal to dt squared
minus
again
some natural radius of some natural size
of the thing
times dh3 squared.
Let me draw one more way of thinking
about the
the negative curved space.
You can't do you cannot
take the whole negatively curved space
and embed it in three dimensions let's
take the two-dimensional case.
The two-dimensional sphere you can
nicely embed
in
uh in three dimensions and draw it.
You can't do that for H. It just doesn't
fit together, right? But small patches
of it you can draw. A small patch of it
you can draw. You just can't fit it all
together. And what it looks like is a
saddle shape. It's the saddle surface.
The saddle surface is the uh
is the negatively curved space.
So, you could take small patches of it
and redraw them as embedded in
three-dimensional space but you simply
can't fit them together to form the
whole hyperbolic plane nicely.
Okay, that's the hyperbolic plane.
Here's Friedman Robertson Walker
or FRW I promised not to use the name
names. FRW
But now it's not K equals plus one
it is K equals minus one simply meaning
negative curved space.
Okay.
We will attach that number K equals plus
one or minus one to these two cases.
Then there's one more FRW
geometry
which also there's one other kind of
homogeneous space.
We have two kinds of homogeneous space
positive curved for the sphere negative
curved for the hyperbolic plane. There's
one more case which sort of sits
uh just between them.
Um the dividing line the dividing line
between hyper between negative curved
and positive curved is flat space.
Flat space can either be thought of as
the limit of an infinitely big well just
think of it as
as just flat space. Let's not think of
it as any limit. Just flat space.
For that the tau squared
is just equal to dt squared minus a of t
squared
times
dx squared plus dy squared plus dz
squared
good old flat space.
Ordinary flat Euclidean space
this though representing the tendency
for uh
uh
for things to separate so to speak.
This would be the metric of FRW
and what would you put here?
K equals zero.
Okay, these are the three
Of course, these are not the only
possible cosmologies you could think
about.
These are the three homogeneous
cosmologies
uh and they are sort of the classic
classic
three cases.
All right, are there any questions about
the geometry of these things up till
now?
Yeah.
Yeah, if if you would project
like do the projection of
either one either the positive or
negative one to a plane and you would
were tracking like a signal on that
continent projection of it uh
if you watch a light go from Perth to
Sydney and you project it
um the when the projection the the
velocity of the light would tend to be
uh transformed as well. Yeah, well uh
for example yeah yeah yeah
I think I know what you're saying and I
think you're absolutely right. On the
projection for example
uh let's let's first of all completely
forget the fact that the universe
expands for a minute.
Just take it as a fixed
as a fixed radius.
Then of course on the sphere it takes a
finite amount of time for a signal to go
from the North Pole to the South Pole
but in the
which is true
in general but on the projection
on the projection the
the North Pole looks like it's an
infinite distance away. It's not really
an infinite distance away. It's just an
infinite
uh distance on the image. So, that must
mean that light rays
when they move go faster and faster the
further out you are.
Okay, and that's true.
Not that they don't really go faster and
faster. They just go faster and faster
on the diagram because a given amount of
ordinary distance corresponds to a
larger distance on the projection. Here
light rays go slower and slower.
In not really but in the figure.
Because it has to take an infinite
amount of time for them to escape to an
infinite distance so the only way that
can be is if on the drawing on the
projection it will look like light rays
go slower and slower.
Okay, I I think that's what you're
asking. Yeah. Right. Can you use the
looking at uh
objects far away to determine the
flatness? Yes.
Well
the
it's really angles that
No, no because you can't get
not easy to find out how fast light is
moving out there.
Um
Look, measuring distances is is
let's come to it. That this this
what you said is true that the speed of
light as measured
on the uh on the projections varies from
place to place.
Is it particularly useful? I probably
is. I just can't think of a
of an example right now.
What I wanted to get to
but I think I would like to
um to rest for about uh
about five or six minutes. Take a little
rest for five or six minutes. And then I
want to come back to the connection.
Now we're set up to talk about the
connection
between
the Newtonian equations of cosmology
that we've used over and over. We've
called them the FRW equations
and the general relativity of these
different metrics. So, let's take five
minutes and uh take a break and then
come back.
I'd like to finish up tonight
by just discussing the connection
between equations that we've already
seen and Einstein's equations which I
didn't want to do earlier because in
order to understand the full uh impact
of uh of general relativity it's
important to understand these three
cases and to combine them together
uh to see the point.
Before I talk about Einstein's equations
a very very brief review
of the Newtonian version of cosmology.
I'll just remind you of how we thought
about it. We said again
put ourselves at the center
look at a galaxy moving away from us.
Let's put it on the x axis just
arbitrarily.
We've got a galaxy
receding away from us according to the
Hubble law.
And look at the equate the Newtonian
equations describing the motion of that
galaxy moving away.
What we said was
the only mass which contributes
to the gravitational pull on that object
toward us
is the mass contained within a sphere.
That's Newton's theorem.
Newton's theorem says
that for any spherically symmetric mass
distribution
the only force on an object is the force
of the material inside the sphere
at radius equal to the distance of the
object itself.
So, we
simply said all we have to do then
is imagine all the mass in the sphere is
concentrated at the center M.
All the mass within that sphere.
And then write Newton's equations
for this object moving away. Obviously
again, there are three possibilities.
The first possibility is that it's
moving away with a velocity larger than
the escape velocity.
Then it will just continue to go.
Less than the escape velocity, in which
it will turn around and fall back toward
the center.
And exactly at the escape velocity. So,
again, there are three cases. Now, there
was also
uh
other divisions.
If we simply talked about ordinary
non-relativistic matter, in other words,
galaxies which were
flowing with the flow,
then we wrote that
uh that the um that the energy density
we wrote things in terms of the energy
density or the mass density. That the
mass density rho went like the mass
divided by a cubed. There were other
possibilities if it was radiation in
here, then the energy density would be
uh would go as one over a to the fourth.
And we also talked about vacuum energy.
Vacuum energy was a component to energy
which didn't change as uh as the sphere
changes.
But uh that was the basic setup.
Newton's equations applied to a galaxy.
And you apply it to any galaxy
anywheres, and you get the same equation
of motion for a.
But in particular, the energy
conservation equation, just ordinary
energy conservation for this object
can be written in a very simple form.
The kinetic energy
was just proportional to
a dot squared.
This distance is proportional to a.
The distance to any given galaxy is
proportional to the scale factor.
So, the connect I won't write the
details. I'm just I'm just reminding you
now. There was a term a dot squared.
Then there was potential energy.
And the potential energy
um we put on the other side of the
equation
with some potential energy.
And I'll just remind you what the
equation looked like by the time we
manipulated a little bit. We divided it
by a squared.
And eventually got on the right-hand
side the energy density
rho or the mass density.
The mass density on the right-hand side.
Let's uh let's put it back. It goes this
way.
But then there was another term on the
right-hand side which we set to zero. It
had to do whether with what the energy
of the outgoing particle was, what the
end the energy was. The energy could be
greater than zero, less than zero, or
equal to zero. The case that we studied
was the case where you're right at the
um
uh escape velocity.
If you're not right at the escape
velocity, there's another term here uh
which is just the total energy, a
constant. And the way that it came into
the equations was on the right-hand side
some number
which I don't remember what I called it.
I may have just called it a K.
Uh let's call it some number
divided by a squared.
It looks a little bit fun. Let's put
Let's put the
Shall I go over that or does everybody
remember it well enough?
Everybody remembers it?
Okay.
Hm?
This was the basic equation of
cosmology. We left this term out.
There's no good reason to leave that
term out. Um although empirically, it is
known to be very small.
So, as a as an empirical fact, it's a
good approximation to leave it out. But
as a conceptual thing, there's no reason
to leave it out. And uh
we should come back to it. But in order
to come back to it, we really do need to
think about Einstein's general theory of
relativity.
Which we're not going to do in detail.
We did it in some we studied it in some
detail last quarter.
I'm just going to tell you the results
of calculations, and
you can fill in how you do them.
By now you should know enough to be able
to do them, but uh
it'd be a little bit tedious.
Not too.
Okay.
We start
with
the FRW
form
for the geometry.
Let's take the case of the sphere first.
Let's take the case the top case, the
sphere first. Okay, we start with that
type of geometry.
The only unknown in it is a of t. But
when I say an unknown, I mean a
time-dependent unknown. In other words,
there's an unknown function in there.
Maybe it's known or not un unknown, but
it is the dynamical uh degree of
freedom. It's the degree of freedom
which tells us how the universe expands
and so forth. So, we take that form with
a general function a of t.
And then we're going to impose
Einstein's field equations and determine
some information about a of t. Now,
we're not going to actually do it. I'm
going to tell you what happens when you
do when you do it, though.
So, let's start with Einstein's field
equations. I'll just remind you what
they are.
They involve the curvature tensor.
And in particular, they involve the
Ricci tensor.
R mu nu.
Minus g mu nu. Now, you're not going to
you're not going to need to know the
details of this if you
haven't studied general relativity.
I'm I'll tell you the facts.
But uh but I'm writing this for those
who
have followed
the previous uh quarter.
Anybody remember what this tensor is
called?
R mu nu is the Ricci tensor. It's made
up out of the curvature tensor. G mu nu
is the metric, except the inverse
metric. And R is the uh is the uh Ricci
scalar. It's the curvature scalar.
And this is a four-dimensional now. This
is now the four-dimensional space-time
curvature tensors. Anybody remember what
that's called?
It's called the Einstein tensor, and
it's usually written G mu nu.
But the important thing is it only
involves the geometry. It's a thing
which involves geometry.
And it involves the curvature of the
space-time geometry, not the spatial
geometry, but the full space-time
geometry.
That's the left-hand side of Einstein's
equations. So, the left-hand side
space-time geometry.
Right-hand side is the sources of the
gravitational field, and those were
energy and momentum. The energy momentum
was summarized
in terms of another tensor called the
energy momentum tensor.
All right. So, on the right-hand side we
have the energy momentum tensor T mu nu.
And I think there is let's see um
I think there's a 4 pi
Newton's constant there if I remember.
Uh so,
just a few words about what's on the
right-hand side.
Oh, and mu and nu go from zero or go
from
over four possibilities, x, y, z, and t.
So, this is four-dimensional space-time
geometry.
And there was an equation like this for
each mu and nu. Those are the Einstein
equations. How many are there all
together?
Uh
mu and nu can go from one to four, so 4
* 4 is 16, but uh the tensor is
symmetric and it has some symmetries.
How many equations? 10, I think there
are 10 equations all together.
10 equations all together. But we only
get
First of all, we only need to know about
one of them.
The right-hand side
the
These are the components of the energy
momentum tensor, which mean things like
energy density or mass density,
depending on whether we want to use E
equals mc squared to relate energy to
mass.
I know reason why we shouldn't.
When C is equal to one,
the right-hand side contains things like
energy density and momentum density and
so forth.
We're only going to need one of these
equations. Um
the reason we're only going to need one
of these equations is because we've
already assumed so much about the
structure of the geometry, there's
really only one unknown.
Now, of course, we've assumed an
enormous amount. We've assumed that the
geometry is homogeneous.
Uh we've assumed that the space is a
sphere.
And so we made a we've made a lot of
um restrictions on the nature of the
geometry. And so we really only need one
differential equation, one equation to
tell us how A varies.
What's the natural one to pick? The
natural one to pick is the one with
both mu and nu equal to time components.
So, you can do that. You can write down
that R 00
minus
G00
R
is equal to 4 pi G. And what's T00?
Hm?
The energy density.
It's the energy density. We've already
called that we've already named that
rho.
The right-hand side is energy density.
The left-hand side is geometry.
Okay.
Next.
We want to calculate, we're not going to
do this, but you in principle you know
how to do this.
The
you calculate the energy momentum tensor
from the metric by differentiating it
the couple of times, calculating
Christoffel symbols, doing whatever it
is you're supposed to do to calculate
the the curvature tensor.
If necessary, you go look up in a book
what the you know what the curvature
tensor is for a geometry like that.
And here's what you find. You find there
are two kinds of terms. The first kind
of term has to do with the fact just
that the geometry is time dependent. It
would be there even if space was flat.
If space was flat, but the scale factor
was time dependent,
there would be a space-time curvature.
Not a space curvature, but a space-time
curvature.
And
if you work that out, spend a little bit
of time with it, you find that these two
terms combine together to give you
I I will I will figure out the
coefficient later. There's a numerical
coefficient. I'll figure it out later by
knowing the answer, but it's
proportional
guess what?
to A dot over A
squared.
So, if you work out for
the for the flat space case, the flat
space means flat
space space, not flat space-time. K
equals zero, the K equals zero case.
You take that metric and plug it into
the formulas for curvature,
calculate R00 minus G00 R, and you will
get A dot over A squared.
Okay. So, the first thing you'll find is
for the flat space case, K equals zero,
A dot over A squared is just 4 pi
G rho.
And of course, that's not quite right.
If you if we actually did the Newtonian
calculation,
we would have gotten
8 pi over 3 here
times G rho.
And so that leads me to believe that
when you actually carry out this
uh this calculation,
that the Einstein tensor here is three
halves of this.
Many years ago, I checked this. I've
never checked it since. I know that it's
true
that that there's actually a three
halves that comes out here. So, that
when you calculate A dot over A squared,
you get
2 * 4 is 8 / 3, 8 pi over 3 G rho.
Uh and you can check that.
Oh, there's a half here. I'm sorry.
There's one half.
There's always a half here.
And somehow these two combine
to give you the three halves.
The sign somehow gives you a two not
somehow, does work out in such a way
that you don't get 1/2 A dot over A
squared, but actually three halves.
Okay, so that's that's the flat space
case.
Now, there's another term in the
curvature,
which would be there
even if the scale factor wasn't changing
with time.
If the scale factor wasn't changing with
time, but if space was curved,
no change no no time dependence, but
curved space,
then again, space-time has curvature.
Just by virtue of the fact that space
has curvature.
So, when space has curvature, there's an
additional contribution here.
And guess what? That contribution
is
apart from numerical factor, let's say 4
pi
uh
4 pi What did I have there? G
times rho.
The other factor that's here
is zero when K is equal to zero,
but for the other two cases, it it's
plus K divided by A squared.
Now, this is probably not true. This is
probably three halves of this.
It's probably three halves of this.
Where K is either plus minus one or
zero.
So, the meaning of this equation then,
let's let's get rid of the three halves
by multiplying.
It becomes 8 pi over 3.
Again,
this is the space-time
or this is the Einstein tensor
when ordinary space is flat,
and it comes from the time dependence of
the scale factor,
oscillation or whatever it is of the
scale factor.
This would be there even if the scale
factor was not time dependent, just from
the curvature of space.
Right?
It comes in with a positive sign for the
sphere and a negative sign for the
hyperbolic plane. Positive curvature, it
comes with a positive term.
Negative curvature, with a negative
term.
This is Einstein's equations when you go
and plug in that particular geometry
into
the Einstein field equations. And so
what do you get? You get exactly
minus
zero for flat space-time. Uh sorry,
excuse me, for flat space.
And otherwise K over A squared. Period.
That's it. Don't you get get a
a factor like
R or something like that?
What is R? Uh
the the radius of curvature is this.
That's this. That's 1 over A squared
here. That's it. That's it. Okay. Right.
Okay, so good. So, for simple
geometries,
curvature is usually just 1 over the
radius of curvature squared.
That's all curvature is for a sphere or
a uniformly curved surface. For a
uniformly curved surface,
curvature has units incidentally of
inverse length squared.
For a given
shape, the curvature will be inverse to
this to
uh to the radius of the thing squared.
So, that's what this is here. And it's
either plus one, minus one, or zero,
depending on which of the cases we're
talking about. Okay, so don't think of K
as a number that can take on any value.
It's either plus one, minus one, or
zero.
You could have K take any value if you
redefine A. Say it again. If you
redefine A,
uh you can you can get K to be any
value. Okay, good.
Under what circumstances can you
redefine A? And what
and to what extent have we defined A?
No, no, you're
you're asking the right question. Um
for the flat space case,
there is no unique definition of A. We
can rescale A.
Uh there's no particular thing to
compare it with. All right? But in that
case, K is zero, so you can't change it.
In the other two cases, there's a
natural scale for A. In the spherical
case, we can take it to be the radius of
the sphere.
All right? If we take it to be the
radius of the sphere itself,
then K is plus one.
In the negatively curved case,
in the negatively curved there's also a
notion of radius of curvature for a
negatively curved space. I won't tell
you I won't describe it in detail.
Uh
but again, in that case, it's just minus
one.
What are the other values of T? What is
the other one? Are all the other values
of the energy momentum tensor zero? Uh
no, not in general.
Not in general.
Uh for example, the space space
components
uh can be the pressure.
Okay? So, for the matter dominated
universe, the pressure is zero.
For the radiation dominated uh universe,
the pressure is 1/3 of the energy
density. We did that the last time.
Uh we will
and remember, we had an equation
just mo- mostly definition that pressure
is equal to W, definition of W, times uh
what do we call energy density? Rho, I
guess.
And uh the three cases of interest with
W equals zero,
zero pressure, that's called matter
dominated.
W equals
1/3,
that's called radiation dominated.
Mhm?
Say it again?
And minus one for
uh
W equals minus one
for vacuum energy.
So, if you just had matter, all the
other all the other components of T
would be zero?
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Um
Right. But, the main point is since
there's only one
arbitrary function in this uh in this
setup, in this
again, we've assumed a lot.
But, once you make all those
assumptions, there's one arbitrary
function, so you really only need one
equation.
Uh you could choose you could choose
other ones. This one's the most
convenient.
Yes, K is equal to plus one for the
sphere, minus one for the hyperbolic
plane, and uh and zero for the flat
space.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay, so we see that Newton's uh
Newton's rules don't really lead us
astray. They give us the right answer,
but
the Einstein equations adds one new
ingredient. It tell
We can think of
this K in two ways.
From the Newtonian point of view, it
simply has to do with whether
we're above or below the escape
velocity.
Okay?
From the Einstein point of view, it has
to do with whether we're above or below
the escape velocity, but also what the
geometry of space is.
Okay?
Now,
I think we can end there for tonight.
I think I've reached uh a good point to
stop.
Um what I should spend a little bit of
time next time is just discussing the
significance of the cosmological
constant and how it affects the behavior
of the solutions,
but again, let me just point out right
now, at least before there was a
cosmological constant, pre-cosmological
constant, there was a tight relationship
between whether you were above or below
the escape velocity and whether space
was positively curved, negatively
curved, or zero curved. How so? If space
was positively curved, K equals plus
one, and that meant you were below the
escape velocity, the implications being
the universe would expand and then
re-contract. You can see that in the
equations. We'll study the equations a
little bit further and see that. I'm a
little too tired now to go through it.
Uh if K is bigger than one, is one, is
plus one, sorry, if K is minus one,
then you're above the escape velocity,
and the universe just continues to
expand. And K equals zero is the
marginal case, the knife edge in
between, where it does continue to
expand, but at an ever decreasing rate.
So, that's the new thing that general
relativity adds into this analysis. Uh
it adds many things, but that's the
central thing that it that that it does,
is it connects the question of
uh above or below the escape velocity to
the question of geometry,
whether the geometry is flat,
round like a sphere, or saddle-shaped
like uh like the hyperbolic plane.
So, it's a it provides a correlation, a
new kind of correlation.
Uh
and uh that brings us to the conclusion
for tonight, and I'm going home and
going to sleep, and I will not see you
next week, unless you're in England.